Finding Aid for J. Raleigh Nelson papers, 1893-1957
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
J. Raleigh Nelson papers
1893-1957
Nelson, J. Raleigh (Joseph Raleigh)
852058 Aa 2; UAm
Professor of engineering English, counselor to foreign students, and founder of the International Center of the University of Michigan; correspondence, subject files, writings, photographs, and family letters.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
4.5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Nelson (donor no. 2874 ) and came to the library in 1961.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
J. Raleigh Nelson was born in Bement, Illinois on May 8, 1873. He later moved with his family to Ann Arbor, Michigan. He received his B.A. degree in 1894 from the University of Michigan and then moved to Chicago where he taught English and Latin for six years at John Marshall High School and for eight years at the Lewis Institute. In the meantime, he had received his M.A. degree in 1903 from the University of Michigan.
In 1908, Nelson returned to the U-M in 1908 to assist in an experimental program in the teaching of English to engineering students. He eventually became chairman of the Department of English in the College of Engineering and adviser to foreign engineering students.
In 1933, Nelson was appointed university counselor to foreign students. This led in 1938 to the founding of the International Center where he was director until his retirement in 1943.
In addition to his university responsibilities, Nelson was author of a volume of poetry Lady Unafraid, a biography of his mother Rebecca Jewel Francis Nelson, as well as professional writings.
Throughout his career, Nelson was also involved in various community organizations, including the Starr Commonwealth for Boys and the Ann Arbor Community Fund. He died January 1, 1961.
The J. Raleigh Nelson collection is comprised of the following series: Family papers; Correspondence, Subject files, Miscellaneous, and Photographs. The correspondence and subject files concern the University of Michigan School of Engineering, his work with foreign students, particularly those from Latin America, student dramatic productions for which Nelson was director, the proposed University College, the activities and affairs of class of 1894, and his work as chairman of Tappan Reunion Committee which attempted to bring alumni from the years of the Tappan Presidency to University for a reunion in June 1930. The collection also includes manuscripts of his writings, photographs, and letters received from his mother.
Subjects:
Ironton (Mich.); Nelson, J. Raleigh (Joseph Raleigh); Tappan, Henry Philip, 1805-1881.; Theater--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan. Class of 1894.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan--Dramatics.Dramatics.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.; University of Michigan. International Center.; University of Michigan. University College.; Students, Foreign--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Clifton (Mich.); Clifton (Mich.)--Mining.; Mining--Michigan--Clifton.; Nelson, J. Raleigh (Joseph Raleigh); University of Michigan. Class of 1894.; University of Michigan--Dramatics.Dramatics.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.; University of Michigan. International Center.; University of Michigan. Gilbert and Sullivan Society.; Students, Foreign--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Gilbert, W. S. (William Schwenck), 1836-1911--Performances--Michigan.PerformancesMichigan.; Sullivan, Arthur, Sir, 1842-1900--Performances--Michigan.PerformancesMichigan.
- Family papers
  - Letters from mother, Rebecca Jewell Nelson, 1901-1904 (Box 5)
- Correspondence, 1898-1957
  - 1898-1919 (Box 1)
  - 1920-1929 (Box 1)
    (including report of Committee on University Theatre, 1924)
  - 1930-1934 (Box 1)
  - 1935-1936 (Box 1)
  - 1937-1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940 (Box 1)
  - 1941 (Box 1)
  - 1942, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1943, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1947-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1957 (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Letters of condolence received after the death of Nelson's mother, 1916; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Rotary Club papers, 1933-1938 (Box 1)
  - Starr Commonwealth for Boys papers, 1934-1939 (Box 1)
  - European trip correspondence, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Mexican trip correspondence, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Proposed University College papers, 1927; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - "Combination" courses papers, 1927 (Box 1)
  - Tappan Reunion correspondence, 1930; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Class of 1894 (largely alumni material), 1894-1939; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Latin-American students (concerning)
    - Undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1933-1940 (Box 2)
    - 1941 (Box 2)
    - 1942 (Box 2)
    - 1943 (Box 2)
  - Teaching of English to foreign students, 1941; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan School of Engineering (concerning)
    - Undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1916-1919 (Box 2)
    - 1920-1925 (Box 2)
    - 1926-1929 (Box 2)
    - 1930-1936 (Box 2)
    - Engineering English courses, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Reading lists, undated, for Nelson's courses (Box 2)
  - Papers, concerning miscellaneous subjects, undated (Box 2)
  - Notebooks concerning miscellaneous subjects, 1895-1925 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous articles, poetry and manuscripts of books, including manuscript of Lady Unafraid (Box 3)
  - Papers concerning plays directed by Nelson (Box 4)
  - Account books of Sweet Briar Farm, Ironton, 1913-1928 (Box 4)
- Photographs
  - Class of, 1894 (Box 4)
  - Cliff Mine (Box 4)
  - International Center (Box 4)
  - Portraits (Box 4)
  - Gilbert and Sullivan Society (Folder 1)
  - International Center (Folder 1)